<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sports Data Blog</title>
    <link>https://dwillis.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sports Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dwillis.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Are College Teams Passing More on First Down?</title>
      <link>https://dwillis.github.io/2022/11/10/are-college-teams-passing-more-on-first-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dwillis.github.io/2022/11/10/are-college-teams-passing-more-on-first-down/</guid>
      <description>library(tidyverse) library(cfbfastR) tictoc::tic() pbp &amp;lt;- data.frame() seasons &amp;lt;- 2014:cfbfastR:::most_recent_cfb_season() progressr::with_progress({ pbp &amp;lt;- cfbfastR::load_cfb_pbp(seasons) }) tictoc::toc() ## 43.313 sec elapsed Most college football teams run more often on first down than they pass. Unless your coach is Mike Leach or you play for Indiana this year, that is.
Leach, the current coach at Mississippi State and inventor of the prolific “Air Raid” offense, has long favored passing over the ground game, but most teams don’t play that way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Best and Worst Red Zone Teams in the NFL</title>
      <link>https://dwillis.github.io/2022/11/03/the-best-and-worst-red-zone-teams-in-the-nfl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dwillis.github.io/2022/11/03/the-best-and-worst-red-zone-teams-in-the-nfl/</guid>
      <description>Scoring from inside the red zone is a good thing for NFL teams. Doing it consistently is even better. The Miami Dolphins began the season with the league’s highest rate of scoring success inside opponents’ 20 yard line. Did they keep it up?
Using Expected Points Added, a metric that tries to quantify how much a play increases or decreases a team’s chances of scoring, ESPN reported that through the first three weeks of the season that the Dolphins had one of the best records in expected points added per play in the red zone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Staying on Offense in the Big Ten</title>
      <link>https://dwillis.github.io/2022/10/06/staying-on-offense-in-the-big-ten/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dwillis.github.io/2022/10/06/staying-on-offense-in-the-big-ten/</guid>
      <description>Staying on Offense in the Big Ten The Big Ten had some of the nation’s more prolific offenses last season. I’m going to make a bar chart of the teams’ average number of offensive plays over the course of the season so I can see which team was lining up the most on average. To do that, I’ll need the game stats from last season and will need to focus on just the Big Ten schools.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
